Good morning everybody.
Killed and quiet. Need a bit of introduction?
Yeah, of course. Okay, so okay, today's דף daf, *daf* is קט"ז
*Kuf Tes Zayin*, 116, end of the penultimate פרק perek, *perek* and
beginning of the ultimate פרק perek. *perek*. Okay, so I just like
saying the word penultimate.
Okay, so we pick up on קט"ז עמוד א׳ *Kuf Tes Zayin
Amud Aleph*
and we have been discussing the issue about taking רחיים ורכב reychayim
v'rachev, *recheim varechev* which are a prohibition of כלי kli שעושים בו
אוכל נפש *kli she'osim bo ochel nefesh* that makes sort of
that's done to create food and interesting questions particularly to two examples.
I mean the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was talking about the larger issue
about that there's a more that it's not just the רחיים ורכב
reychayim v'rachev, *recheim varechev*, the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* כי
נפש הוא חובל *ki nefesh hu chovel* includes other things of the
same category and the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* focus was when you take
רחיים ורכב *recheim varechev* do you also get for the generic לאו
*lav*? But in the middle of that it gave an example or
at the end of that it gave an example about taking scissors
and taking a team of oxen. So that seems to broaden the
definition a great deal. Like how are scissors אוכל נפש *ochel nefesh*?
Maybe it's done maybe maybe it means like a barber scissors, did
it mean really anything that's a your professional tools? You know, oxen
are not כלים Keilim, *keilim*, are not like you know inanimate types
of vessels that are fashioned, they're living beings. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*
narrows those. He says that those are vegetable scissors, you know, for
cutting trimming vegetables, that doesn't mean the team of oxen, it actually
means some type of a you know the yoke itself and it's
not oxen that are plowing, it's oxen that are threshing and therefore
we're dealing directly with the food. But obviously that leaves us with
a lot of questions of exactly what the scope is of those
types of vessels. It should also be remembered that we're not talking
about just about a poor person. The poor person is specifically mentioned
in the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* in terms of entering into the home.
These other things do not specifically mention a poor person. So let's
see now how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* concludes this discussion. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Middle of קט"ז עמוד א׳ *Kuf Tes
Zayin Amud Aleph*, it starts with ההוא גברא *hahu gavra*. I'll launch
on the word גברא *gavra*. Literally halfway down in the middle of
the page. Okay, ההוא גברא
*hahu gavra*, there was a person דחבל סכינא דאשכבתא מחבריה *dechaval sakina
de'ashkavta mechavreih*. He took a butcher's knife from his friend. Somehow the
word אשכבתא *ashkavta* means butcher's knife? I mean סכינא *sakina* means knife.
Okay, he so and he he took it as collateral.
Now it sounds like he was in violation.
What? Doesn't matter. The issue is אוכל נפש *ochel nefesh*. These are
כלים *keilim* that deal directly with food. And as I think Michael
reminded me at the end, you know, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* even points
out another point that I you could say it's ironic, I don't
think it's ironic, but if you take a look at תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafot* כלים שעושים בהם אוכל נפש *keilim she'osim bahem ochel nefesh*, this
tiny little תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, he says נראה לר״י דדווקא כלים אבל
אוכלים עצמם מותר לחבול *nireh le'Ri dedavka keilim aval ochlim atsmam mutar
lachvol*. You can actually take food itself, you just can't take the
vessel, you know, the implement, which you could say that's crazy, but
no, it makes sense. You know, it's the old story it's the
old line, you know, give me a fish, feed me for a
day, teach me to fish, feed me for life. So you take,
you know, the actual implement and the person now doesn't have ongoing
the ability to do that. You know, you take food, it's just
the immediate. Anyway, so this is a type of a implement that
is used for אוכל נפש *ochel nefesh*, so it seems he was
in violation. אתא לקמיה דאביי *ata likamei de'Abaye*, came to אביי Abaye
*Abaye*. אמר ליה זיל אהדריה *amar lei zil ahadreih*, give it back
to him דהוה ליה כלי kli שעושים בו אוכל נפש *dehavei lei
kli she'osim bo ochel nefesh*, you violated the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*. And
you could say okay, I violated it but might as well keep
it, but no, clearly there's a sense and I'll discuss in a
minute תוספות's Tosafos *Tosafot's* discussion about this of trying to rectify what
you've done. You weren't supposed to take it, so give it back.
Okay, ותקום בדינא עליה aliya. *vekum bedina aleih*, and if you have
some claim against him, then go sue him in court but you
but you have to first give back the כלי kli *kli* you
took that in violation. רבא Rava אמר *Rava amar*, רבא Rava *Rava*
says לא Lo, צריך למיקם בדינא עליה aliyah *lo tsarich lemikam bedina
aleih*, he does not need to like go to court, meaning he's
got leverage here that will prevent him from the need of going
to court. What's leverage? ויכול לטעון עד כדי דמיהן *veyachol lit'on ad
kedei demeihen*.
Since right now he's holding on to this object and there were
no witnesses that he seized the object, he could just claim that
it was always his or that the guy, you know, sold it
to him. So basically he could say before I return this to
you, like I you know, at least let's say because the question
is I'm going to return it and I'll have no leverage. I
don't have witnesses that he owes me the money, I don't have
a שטר *shtar*. So I'm going to be stuck. So רבא Rava.
*Rava* says don't worry. Before you return it you can say you
owe me, let's say the butcher's knife was worth a hundred dollars,
you know, you owe at even if and let's say the loan
was I don't know five hundred dollars, but nevertheless don't give up
the butcher's knife. Say you owe me a hundred dollars and I
should be believed that you owe me a hundred dollars and that
this I took as collateral because I could have just claimed all
along that this was mine, that you sold this to me. So
it's a מיגו migo *migo*. It's a מיגו migo *migo* exactly.
Except you're in violation of what you're supposed to do, you're supposed
to
be ממשכנו בביתו *memashkeno beveito*. Yes, you were totally forget ממשכנו בביתו
*memashkeno beveito*, this is a כלי kli שעושה אוכל נפש *kli she'oseh
ochel nefesh*. You weren't supposed to be ממשכן *memashken* it at all,
this כלי kli *kli*, doesn't matter what. without בית דין. beis din
So you really shouldn't have this כלי at all. So it's interesting
that רבא Rava, is able to sort of bracket that problem and
let him use this כלי that he got in violation to give
him leverage in this case. But that's what רבא Rava is advising
him. Yes, you transgressed, you have to do תשובה teshuva about that,
but before you give it back, you can claim that he owes
you at least the value of the כלי because you could have
always claimed that the כלי was always yours.
Okay. Usually a מיגו migo doesn't involve a lie. What? מיגו migo
usually doesn't involve a lie, does it?
מיגו always involves a lie. Believe me when I say X because
if I wanted to I could have lied and said Y.
I could have lied, not
if I could have said a better... Yeah, that's it. The better
claim is a lie. If X is the true claim, then the
better claim is the other claim is a lie. That's always what
a מיגו is. Okay, but anyway, but there's other problems here. It's
a מיגו להוציא, migo lehotzi, you're trying to take money away from
somebody. Anyway, the other problem is that we tolerated בית bayis דין
using this even though it came through violation. That's I think the
biggest חידוש. chiddush. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. ואביי
לית ליה האי סברא? Va'Abaye leis lei hai sevara?
Now the גמרא Gemara totally again like brackets the problematics of the
fact that this was in violation and says, yeah, that's actually a
good point. Why did אביי Abaye make him give it back right
away? Why didn't אביי Abaye say that you should be able to
use this as leverage to claim that that's owed to you? מאי
שנא מהני עיזי דאכלי חושלא בנהרדעא? Mai shena mehani izi de'achli chushla
be'Nahardea?
There were these goats that ate חושלא, chushla, whatever חושלא chushla is,
some type of vegetation, in נהרדעא. Nahardea. They destroyed somebody's field. ואתא
מריה דחושלא ותפסינהו, Ve'asa marei de'chushla vesafsinhu, the owner of this חושלא
chushla came
and he seized them. וקא טעין טובא, Veka ta'ein tuva,
and he said before I'm going to return these goats, I want
you to pay me for the damage. And I'm claiming that the
damage was a thousand dollars. Now there was no way to exactly
assess the damage, right? There were no witnesses exactly how much the
field was worth before the goats ate from it, right? I said
you came into my field and you ate all these prize strawberries,
they were the best strawberries of the season, you know, I could
have got a thousand dollars for the whole crop. Who's to believe
me? Like I don't have any evidence. Okay, but I'm holding onto
your goats and I'm saying if you don't pay me, you should
believe me that that was what the damage was because I could
always claim that these goats are my goats. Okay, so you see
the exact same idea that you're able to seize somebody's property and
if there's no evidence that you seized it and you could legitimately
be believed to claim that they're yours, you could use it as
leverage as a way to be believed about what the person owes
you. So why should this case be different? Oh wait, let's finish
the sentence... let's finish the phrase. דאמר אבוה דשמואל, De'amar avuh de'Shmuel,
the father of שמואל Shmuel said: יכול לטעון עד כדי דמיהן, Yachol
lit'on ad kedei demeihen,
he's believed as to how much the damage was up to the
value of the goats that he seized. So how is this any
different? So the גמרא Gemara says: התם לאו מידי דעביד להשאולי ולאוגורי
הוא. Hasam lav midi de'avid le'ahsholi ule'agorei hu.
No, no, no. Goats are not something that normally is lent out
or rented out. And therefore, if you're holding onto goats, the question
is, you know, the general principle is: חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם
הרי הוא שלו. Chazaka mah she'tachas yad adam harei hu shelo. The
presumption is anything you're holding onto is yours for chattel, not by
land. Okay. And therefore, it's like possession is nine-tenths of the law.
So there's a presumption that it's yours. Now, that would not be
true if you saw me driving around a Hertz rent-a-car, I could
not say oh there's a presumption that it's mine. Okay. There are
some things that let's say it's a lawnmower, alright? And we know,
you know, not everybody in town has a lawnmower, you borrow your
next-door neighbor's lawnmower. So you're seen using a lawnmower.
Well, a lawnmower...
so there's some things that are דעבידן להשאיל ולהשכיר de'avidan le'ahshil ule'haskir
that holding onto them does not create a presumption that they're yours
because there's a reasonable assumption that you borrowed them or rented them.
Okay. So goats are not that way. Goats people don't lend their
goats, they don't rent their goats. So if you're holding onto goats,
you have a presumption they're yours and therefore by saying I seized
them but you did this damage you're believed because you could have
said they were yours. Whereas a butcher's knife, the גמרא Gemara somehow
assumes that that is something like a lawnmower, you know, that you
borrow and or that sometimes is borrowed and therefore that's אביי's Abaye
point, that you don't have that same presumption. Or as I think
you can go both ways
on cows. Right. So that's the question: what's the threshold of דעביד
להשאיל? de'avid le'ahshil? Okay, but let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes
with this. So the גמרא Gemara says: הכא מידי דעביד להשאולי ולאוגורי
הוא. Hacha midi de'avid le'ahsholi ule'agorei hu. Here in this case,
it's something that normally is rented out and or lent out. So
therefore,
the holding onto it does not create a presumption of ownership and
he doesn't have that leverage. Okay, דשלח רב הונא בר אבין. deshlach
Rav Huna bar Avin. Rav Huna bar Avin sent the following message:
דברים העשויים להשאיל ולהשכיר, Devarim ha'asuyim le'ahshil ule'haskir, things that are normally...
now again, the question is of course what's the threshold? 70% of
the time, 50% of the time? So that's a good question, but
we're not going to figure that out right now. But things that
are normally rented or lent
and somebody claims that he purchased them, because the point is, and
this is important to stress, the fact that it's a presumption that
it's yours is even if we had evidence that yesterday it was
somebody else's.
Okay, so... So Michael, we had everybody saw that Michael's iPhone and
everybody knew it was Michael's and had very distinctive markings on it
and scratches on it or whatever and the next day people see
me walking around with it. And I say, I bought it off
of yeah isn't that Michael's iPhone? What did you do? Give it
back to him. I said, no no no, it is I bought
it off of him. I'd be
believed. Even though you knew it was Michael's yesterday because people buy
and sell things. Okay now you could ask what about things that
people would never sell? That's like the opposite of things that normally
people lend, right? Very personal things that you might presume are never
sold. But anyway, but the point is that you're believed to say
they're yours, לקוחים הם בידי, lekuchim hem beyadi, not that I always
owned them. You're believed to say I purchased them. Yes, we know
yesterday it was somebody else's. But you're believed if you're in possession
of it today to say that you have just purchased them just
yesterday or just a minute ago. Okay that's normally the case. Okay
but if they're normally rented out, you're not believed to say that.
ואמר לקוחים הם בידי אינו נאמן. v'amar lekuchim hem beyadi eino ne'eman.
You're not believed. Now the גמרא Gemara turns back to רבא. Rava
For רבא, Rava does רבא Rava not hold of this point that
if they're normally rented you don't have a you're not believed and
presumably that's the case with this butcher's
knife? ורבא אפיק זוגא דסרבא וספרא דאגדתא מיתמי. v'Rava apik zugga d'sarba
v'safra d'agadata m'yasme. רבא Rava took out a
we're back to a what do you call it? A scissors, but
these are shearing scissors that you would shear a sheep with, okay,
sheep shearing scissors and a book of
אגדתא, Agadata, fascinating, okay presumably אגדתא Agadata rabbinic stories, מיתמי, m'yasme, now
orphans had this. So and he basically said, and the orphans were
claiming that it was their
father's, okay, so listen so there were orphans, okay, I basically brought
evidence that these things used to be mine. I'm claiming I lent
them to the father, the father died, I'd like to get them
back now. And the orphans maybe said no they were always ours
or they said we don't know but we're presuming they're our father's
because he left them in the estate. Okay so they have a
חזקה. chazaka. We should say חזקה מה שתחת יד אדם הרי הוא
שלו. chazaka ma shetachas yad adam harei hu shelo. Maybe the father
bought them off of me even if I claim they were once
mine. And the גמרא Gemara says בדברים העשויים להשאיל ולהשכיר bidvarim ha'asuyim
lehashil ul'haskir and רבא Rava said no, since you proved they were
yours, we're going to take them away from the orphans because we're
going to presume the father didn't buy them because these are things
that are normally lent or rented out. You know, it's like my
lawnmower. I'm shearing my sheep. Hey Michael, could you lend me your
sheep scissors, I'm shearing my sheep today. Okay and he just borrowed
a book, can you lend me a book. So the fact that
the father died, okay whatever meaning, so this is something where holding
on to it is not a presumption of ownership and the fact
that you can prove that they were originally yours means you can
come and take them out of their hands. Okay so one minute,
so you see רבא Rava holds that there's not a חזקה chazaka
on things that
are normally rented out. So why did he hold there was a
חזקה chazaka by this butcher's knife? So the גמרא Gemara, says אמר
לך רבא, amar lach Rava, רבא Rava will tell you, האי נמי,
hai nami, this too, כיון דמפגמא, keivan d'meiphagma, since it depreciates in
value, the butcher's knife, you know over time or maybe over use
or
something, so people don't lend it out. So whatever you know butcher's
knives I guess more delicate, you know more valuable and more delicate,
right, you know sometimes I don't know you can buy these knives
you know now these are kitchen knives, these fancy what are they
you know for hundreds of dollars, right, you know they never so
people have expensive specialty knives that they don't want to lend out.
So this is not normally lent out and therefore he is believed.
So this became a whole discussion of when do you have a
presumption that things that you're holding are yours and it would not
even if you know they used to be somebody else's and it
normally would be except in a case when they're normally rented or
lent. But what sort of it's the larger context is that even
though this guy violated a biblical prohibition to go ahead and seize
this property, now that he's holding on to it we're prepared to
let him use this as leverage in court before he has to
go ahead and return it. רב דב, Rabbi Dov, you had a
question?
No, I did not. Okay, Charlie.
ספרא דאגדתא, sifra d'Agadata, this would imply that at least part of
תורה שבעל פה Torah She-Ba'al Peh was written down by this point?
Yeah, but stories are obviously of a different nature than hard הלכה.
halacha. Michael, yes?
Yeah based on what we were saying earlier about רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, does it make it any better or worse if this stuff
was done after the time for repayment came
and he didn't pay and then you took it?
Yeah well the question about the לא תחבול lo tachvol about רחים
ורכב, rechain v'rachev,
is it only after the זמן הלואה zman halva'ah or even בשעת
הלואה? bish'as halva'ah? I think if I remember correctly that's a מחלוקת
machlokes רמב״ם ראב״ד, Rambam-Ra'avad, I think I mentioned that earlier.
No, no, I mean the גמרא Gemara clearly does not. Yes. סרבלא?
Sarbula?
Is it like a few pages
earlier? Right exactly. So it has two different meanings.
That's a good point. Unless סרבלא... Sarbula... Unless סרבלא Sarbela it means
like if it means like wool, right, maybe that's it because סרבלא
Sarbela means wool, so it's a wool cloak, a thick wool cloak,
and it's a shearing for the sheep's wool. But it's a very
good point, right?
Because before a זוגא, zuga, right, a scissors of סרבלא.
Sarbela. Right, but what Michal is saying is סרבלא Sarbela before it
meant a thick wool coat and here it means wool, but maybe
that's the point, it means wool. Presumably, it still means wool garments.
These are the scissors that can cut wool. Right. Now,
by the way, so I want to make two points before we
turn the page. Number one is this issue about when, how do
you define the circumstances when possession is not a presumption of ownership
about the fact that these types of vessels are normally lent out,
but it's not just a question of these types. What do you
do? You go ahead and look at statistics. How often do people
lend lawnmowers? What don't we look about my relationship with my next-door
neighbor? Is he the nice guy that normally lends it out? Am
I a guy that borrows it? Does he like me? Does he
lend it to me? How much is that a factor? So תוספות
Tosafos. brings another גמרא Gemara. that does just look at that. If
you look at the first line of the תוספות Tosafos והא רבה,
v'ha Rabbah, last תוספות Tosafos of the דף, he says והא רבה
אפקינהו בזוגא דסרבלא וספרא דאגדתא v'ha Rabbah afkinhu b'zuga d'sarbela v'safra d'agadata
ותימא דהכא משמע מטעם דעשוי להשאיל ולהשכיר לחודיה אינו נאמן. v'seima d'hacha
mashma mita'am d'asuy l'hashil u'l'haskir l'chudei eino ne'eman. It's enough that this
is the nature of these types of objects to be lent out.
You just look at like, do people lend out, people in the
generic, lend out lawnmowers? Okay? אינו נאמן לומר לקוחים הם בידי. eino
ne'eman lomar lekuchim heim b'yadi. פרק כל הנשבעין גבי ראוהו שהוציא כלים
תחת כנפיו ואמר לו לקוחין הן אינו נאמן. perek kol hanishba'in gabi
re'uhu she'hotzi keilim tachas kenafav v'amar lo lekuchin hen eino ne'eman. כמר
k'mar ולומר דאינו נאמן אלא, v'lomar d'eino ne'eman ela, when do we
say that you're not believed if they're normally lent out? אלא בבעל
הבית שאינו עשוי למכור כליו. ela b'ba'al habayis she'eino asuy limkor keilav.
First of all, it's only a guy who, that goes like to
my example, people don't let's say sell their iPhone. Only if it's
the type of guy that normally would not sell his vessel. So
that creates an added presumption that if you have it it's because
he lent it to you, not because he sold it to you.
Okay? וכלים שאין דרכם להטמין ומשום דלא צניעא. v'keilim she'ein darkam l'hatmin
u'mishum d'lo tzania. I mean, you look at a lot of other
circumstances to try to determine is there a reason to undermine this
presumption that possession is ownership. Okay. So תוספות Tosafos tried to work
out the difference between the סוגיות, sugyos, but what I want you
to see is, is that how much you just make some generic
statistic, seventy percent of the time those lawnmowers are lent out, or
do you look at the very concrete
specific circumstances to try to, and how much is that important to
challenging the presumption that possession is ownership.
What do you do?
Let's say the scissors are lent out, but you're not the kind
of guy that does that. Right. So that's what תוספות Tosafos, would
do. What do you mean? We haven't even finished the תוספות. Tosafos
It's a whole discussion. I wanted you to see that it's a
problem, it's a question. Now, the other issue is, okay, the other
important question is, the other important thing before we finish this פרק,
perek is the idea that אביי Abaye told him to return it.
Is that was that just like it's a right thing? You were
in violation and you should return it? Or there's two other ways
to think about why he told him to return it, which is,
number one, do we consider the idea do we consider the prohibition
of לא יחבול רחיים ורכב lo yachavol reychayim v'rachev to be ניתק
לעשה, nitak l'aseh, connected to a positive rectifying מצוה? mitzvah? Now, what
positive rectifying מצוה? mitzvah? Well, but that give back only occurs in
the פסוק Pasuk by entering into the house. לא תבוא אל ביתו
לעבוט עבוטו. lo tavo el beiso la'avot avoto. I'm sorry. No, no.
השב תשיב לו את העבוט כבוא השמש. hashev tashiv lo es ha'avot
k'vo hashemesh. I'm sorry. It occurs by, excuse me, by returning
the object that you return on a daily basis. You didn't take
it in violation, right? You took his night clothes in the day
and the day clothes in the night and it says השב תשיב
העבוט כבוא השמש, hashev tashiv ha'avot k'vo hashemesh, right? So do we
learn that השב תשיב, hashev tashiv, returning the collateral in that case
when it wasn't violation, it's just a poor person and a daily
basis, to be a general מצות עשה mitzvas aseh to rectify violations
of these types of taking collateral. So if I took רחיים ורכב,
I took something that was עושה אוכל נפש, oseh ochel nefesh, is
there a מצות עשה mitzvas aseh to return it? That's one question.
Another question, תוספות Tosafos raises this question. We'll look at the תוספות
Tosafos in a second. The other question is, if I take it,
forget the מצות עשה. mitzvas aseh. If I took it, do I
does it work to give me the normal rights that I would
have when I take collateral? And what's the reason it shouldn't? Because
there's a general discussion in the גמרא Gemara in
תמורה, Temurah,
which is אי עביד מהני או לא מהני. ei avid mahni o
lo mahni. If you do something in violation of a תורה Torah
מצוה, mitzvah, does the thing still is it still legally binding what
you did?
Is there still legal effect to your act when it was done
in violation of a תורה Torah מצוה? mitzvah? So here I violated
the מצוה mitzvah and I took the רחיים ורכב, I took the
כלי that's עושה אוכל נפש, oseh ochel nefesh, do I have
property rights in it like I would have in a normal משכון,
mashkon, or do I not because I did it in violation? So
that's two reasons why אביי Abaye. might have told the guy to
return it. Okay. Either he maybe had a מצות עשה, mitzvas aseh,
maybe he even forgetting that, he didn't have the rights to continue
to hold it as a משכון. mashkon. because he was in violation
of because the violation, the fact that he seized it in violation
means that there was no legal effect of his act. So if
you take a look, let's just look at that quick because those
are important questions on the תוספות Tosafos on קט"ו ע"א. Kuf Tes
Vav Amud Aleph. Okay,
he says, the last תוספות, Tosafos turn back a page, וחיב, V'Chayav,
תוספות Tosafos says like this, he says,
let me see if I can find where it starts...
yeah I think like four lines from the bottom?
Yeah.
Okay, it says like this,
ותימא, V'Teima, four lines from the bottom of קט"ו ע"א, Kuf Tes
Vav Amud Aleph, like about five words into the line, when the
תוספות Tosafos says the גמרא, Gemara you know the גמרא Gemara, says
if you took two כלים, you transgressed twice, and תוספות Tosafos says
presumably transgressed twice means
you
get two sets of lashes. So תוספות Tosafos wants to understand why
do you get lashes? He says, ותימא דהיכי לקי, V'Teima DeHeichi Laki,
how do you get lashes for violating ריחיים ורכב? Rechayim VeRachev? והחשיב
לאו דניתק לעשה, VeChashiv Lav DeNitak La'Aseh,
this is what he reads into אביי. Abaye It's connected to a
positive מצוה Mitzvah of returning. How do you know? מדאמר ליה אביי
זיל אהדר, Mid'Amar Lei Abaye Zil Ahadeir, since אביי Abaye told him
to return it, presumably that means that there's a מצות עשה Mitzvat
Aseh to return it. That's a way to read into the גמרא.
Gemara Okay, וכי תימא דמשום הכי אמר ליה לאהדורי, VeChi Teima DeMishum
Hachi Amar Lei L'Ahadorei, maybe no no no, maybe this is why
he told him to return it. דכל מילתא דאמר רחמנא לא תעביד
אי עביד לא מהני, DeChol Milta D'Amar Rachmana Lo Ta'avid Ei Avid
Lo Mahani, if the תורה Torah says don't do something and you
did it, you don't have legal rights, it wasn't legally effective. I
know. The גמרא Gemara says you can't say that. האביי גופיה קאמר
בפרק קמא דתמורה דאי עביד מהני, Ha'Abaye Gufiah Ka'Amar BePerek Kama DeTemurah
De'Ei Avid Mahani, first of all אביי Abaye doesn't hold of that
principle. Okay. So first of all, but that's an interesting question, right?
If you're in violation, do you have legal rights or not? Is
it was it legally effective? And that might be dependent on this
discussion in תמורה. Temurah. Okay, so then תוספות Tosafot says at the
bottom, da da da da da da, I mean let's turn the
page.
So he thinks the reason אביי Abaye told him to return it
was maybe you do have legal rights in this in this object,
maybe you do have, you know, it was effective, but you have
a מצות עשה Mitzvat Aseh to return it. But then תוספות Tosafot
says then why are we talking about lashes? So if you take
a look, תוספות Tosafot says, da da da da da
da, ועוד קשה היכי חשיב ליה אביי, VeOd Kasheh Heichi Chashiv Lei
Abaye, okay, the line starts with the word חשיב, Chashiv, it's
one two three about five lines down, six lines down in the
narrow lines. היכי חשיב ליה אביי ניתק לעשה, Heichi Chashiv Lei Abaye
Nitak La'Aseh,
how could אביי Abaye consider it to be connected to a positive
מצות עשה? Mitzvat Aseh? והלא אשכחן דניתק אקרא, VeHalo Ashkan DeNitak Akara,
the פסוק never said that the prohibition of taking these vessels could
be rectified by a positive... there's no פסוק in the תורה Torah
that says to correct this prohibition. Okay. כדאשכחן גבי השבת אבידה, K'DeAshkan
Gabei Hashavat Aveidah, דלא תבוא בביתו לעבוט עבוטו, DeLo Tavo BeVeito La'Avot
Avoto, דהתם בהדיא
כתיב עשה השב תשיב את העבוט. DeHatam BeHedya Ketiv Aseh Hashev Tashiv
Et Ha'Avot. Okay, so that when you go actually enter into the
house, I was right when I said that. When you enter into
the house the פסוק there at the end speaks about returning the
עבוט, Avot, but here there's no positive מצוה, Mitzvah, it's just don't
take this. וכל מקום אפילו מסקינן דאיסורא ולחייב והכי חזי אביי, VeChol
Makom Afillu Maskinan De'Issura U'Lechayiv VeHachi Chazi Abaye, ויש לומר טעמא דאביי
דאמר ליה לאהדורי, VeYesh Lomar Ta'ama De'Abaye D'Amar Lei L'Ahadorei, maybe the
reason אביי Abaye told him to return it משום דאי עביד לא
מהני, Mishum De'Ei Avid Lo Mahani, go back to what we said
before. Yes, because you are in violation, you did not get property
rights in it. כיון דהשתא שוגג, Keivan DeHashta Shogeg, now what about
the fact that אביי Abaye says that when you're in violation it
does work? So he says no. כיון דהשתא שוגג דאי הוה ידע
דהוא אסור לא הוה עביד, Keivan DeHashta Shogeg De'Ei Hava Yada DeHava
Assur Lo Hava Avid, had he realized he wouldn't have done it,
והוי ליה זכייה בטעות וחוזרת. VeHavi Lei Zechiya BeTa'ut VeChozeret. So maybe
he says no no no. There's a different reason. Not because you
were in violation. But I only seized this because I thought I
had rights. I thought I had I wouldn't do an עבירה. Aveirah.
Had I realized that it was biblically prohibited, I never would have
seized it. So when I seized it to take possession, I was
taking possession in error, right? The reason I didn't get rights was
not because I violated I didn't get rights. The reason I didn't
get rights when I seized this was because had I known I
would have violated I never would have seized it in the first
place, and then you would have rights, then you would have rights.
Okay, so this is a very interesting תוספות Tosafos discussing why did
אביי Abaye say to return it. And he has three possibilities. Number
one, there's a positive מצוה Mitzvah to return it. תוספות Tosafos. says
no, that's not true. There might be a positive מצוה Mitzvah when
you take the cloak to return it on a daily basis, or
maybe when you enter and violate the house to return it, but
taking ריחיים ורכב Rechayim VeRachev there is no positive מצוה Mitzvah to
rectify. Number two, you don't have rights to hold onto it because
since you violated, your act was not legally effective. Okay, the very
fact of violation prevented it from being effective. אי עביד לא מהני.
Ei Avid Lo Mahani. No, that's not true. אביי Abaye holds אי
עביד מהני. Ei Avid Mahani. Number three, the reason it didn't work
is because you didn't wouldn't have wanted to take it had you
known that what you were doing was prohibited. And since you wouldn't
have wanted to take it, therefore your taking of it was בטעות,
BeTa'ut, was an error, and you did not get legal rights. Okay,
so three very interesting interpretations of why when we read the גמרא
Gemara we just thought it was like... Okay, so three very interesting
interpretations. Like when we read the גמרא, Gemara. we just thought it
was a moral point; you shouldn't have taken it, give it back.
But תוספות Tosfos obviously doesn't assume that and he brings in these
various legal reasons why it has to be returned.
Okay, so what's the conclusion, have to give it back or not?
Well, I mean, I mean, the גמרא Gemara concludes, yes, you have
to give it back, but the question whether you should be able
to use it as leverage before you give it back depends on
whether it's אסור להשהות ולהשכיר. assur lahashot ulahaskir. Yes, Charlie.
So I'm an unscrupulous lender and I know that it's prohibited, but
I do it anyway and I run a business like this.
Right,
so, like you also run a business about ריבית. ribbis. What's your
point?
So this thing of 'I wouldn't have done it had I known
it' isn't true.
No, so תוספות Tosfos says, if somebody does know it's prohibited and
does it anyway, then he would have legal rights. He's limiting it
to a case where the guy was in error. Yes.
Can you go back just for one second to the תוספות Tosafot
at the bottom of
קט"ו ע"ב?
kuf tet-vav amud bet?
To the first long line,
והכא נמי השואל ספרים עשוי להשאיל ולהשכיר ואפילו ספרי דאגדתא וכל שכן
שאר ספרים. v'hacha nami hashoel sefarim asui l'hash'il u'l'haskir v'afilu sifrei d'agadata
v'chol shekein sh'ar sefarim. Right, what are those שאר ספרים sh'ar sefarim
he's talking about? He can't be talking about something of a higher
value.
I assume he means a ספר תורה. Sefer Torah.
But then why is it כל שכן? kol shekein? In other words,
I would think it'd be less inclined to lend out unless it's
like for a מצוה. mitzvah.
No, because then he quotes the next
line, צדקתו עומדת לעד זה הכותב ספרים ומשאילן
לאחרים.
tzidkato omedet la'ad zeh hakotev sefarim u'mash'ilan
l'acherim.
To lend out a ספר תורה? Sefer Torah?
Exactly. Yeah. Okay. All right. So הדרן עלך המקבל שדה מחבירו. Hadran
alach Hamikabel Sadeh Mechaveiro. So that was a very nice פרק. perek
We talked about the different פרקים prokim here that deal with biblical
מצוות mitzvos and contrast dealing with the איסור issur of ריבית ribbis
and that פרק perek of איזהו נשך Eizehu Neshech to this one,
which had all these nice, you know, the moral issues were very
much on display, you know, it was much more sort of accessible
and so on. Anyways, so that was a very nice פרק perek
about all those מצוות mitzvos and לא תעשה lo ta'asehs associated with
taking collateral. Now we move to a פרק perek, that seems to
have nothing to do with anything we discussed before, and really in
a way is an introduction into the first פרק perek of בבא
בתרא. Baba Basra. Has to do with, you know, shared ownership of
property, dividing it, and so on, who has rights, etc., etc. Why
is it? Because נזיקין Nezikin was thirty פרקים prokim and you divided
it into three equal sections of ten each, okay? So the line
between בבא קמא Baba Kama and בבא מציעא Baba Metzia works out
very nicely, but the line between בבא מציעא Baba Metzia and בבא
בתרא Baba Basra probably would have been better nine and eleven rather
than ten and ten. Anyways, in some ways you can sort of
see this as paralleling the first פרק, perek, because if you remember
the first פרק is שנים אוחזין בטלית, Shnayim Ochazin B'talit, right? Two
people holding onto a טלית tallit arguing 'it's mine' and so on.
So here there's a similar question of who's, you know, two people
holding onto something, to whom does it belong? So let's take a
look. הבית והעלייה של שנים, Habbayis v'ha'Aliyah shel shnayim, you have a,
you know, you have a house and the upper story and they're
owned by two people.
One person owns the house, one person owns the second story. שנפלו,
shenafalu, and they collapsed, and now everybody wants to claim ownership over
the various building materials.
So שניהם חולקים בעצים ובאבנים ובעפר, shneihem cholkim b'etzim u'v'avanim u'v'afar, they
equally... ובעפר, u'v'afa, they equally divide the wood and the stones and
the dirt, you know, I guess you used good dirt for making
plaster, whatever you use it for. Soil? No, I don't think it's
soil. I think it means specifically building related, we're not talking about
the yard.
רש"י Rashi says that it's proportional. You know, you figure out how
much of the building material was at the bottom level, how much
of the building material was at the top level, right? And then
that's the proportion of the rubble, you know, of that you get,
okay? So ורואים אלו אבנים הראויות להשתבר, v'roim elu avanim hara'uyot l'hishtaber,
and you determine which are the stones that most likely would have
broken, because what you're going to find is you're going to have
a lot of broken stones and you'll have a few whole ones,
okay? So who gets the whole ones, who gets the broken ones?
So with lack of any other evidence, you divide them equally, okay?
And if the bottom level was two-thirds of the building material and
the top level was a third, then you get two-thirds of a
random, you know, of a mix of all the objects, and I
get the other third, and we equally get, you know, the different
types of the objects, okay?
But let's say we can assess where it's more likely that the
broken ones came from and where it's more likely that the whole
ones came from. Like the גמרא Gemara will talk about the fact
about how did the building fall, right? If the building fall like
from the top like this, okay, then the stones that first of
all are distant from the foundation belong to the top story, and
those are probably the ones that are more broken, and the stones
that are closer to the foundation, right, are belong to the bottom
story and those are the ones that are probably more whole. However,
if it fell because like the foundation was shattered and it more
collapsed in its place, so then it's different, it's not far and
close, it's top and bottom. The top of the rubble is probably
the top story, and the bottom of the rubble is probably the
bottom story. And also presumably the top ones will be, I mean
I don't know, but presumably the top ones will be more whole
if it really happened that the bottom was like, you know, something
hit the bottom and
shattered. but presumably the top ones will be more whole. So the
משנה mishnah says that you
assess; if you don't know anything, you just divide it proportionally. But
if you do know, רואין את אלו אבנים הראויות להשתבר, ro'in et
elu avanim hara'uyot lishaber, you would determine which were the ones that
were more likely to break and that person gets those. אם היה
אחד מהם מכיר מקצת אבניו, im haya echad mehem makir miktzat avanav,
now if one of them recognizes some of his stones, נוטלן, notlan,
he says oh yeah I see these are mine, yeah I recognize
them. You might disagree, right? Well, what does the other one say?
Anyway, he gets it, ועלו לו מן החשבון. va'olu lo min hacheshbon.
But then it sort of that gets deducted off of his side.
So if he's entitled to, you know, like whatever, if there's 30
tons of rubble and his you know the bottom section was two-thirds
of the building material, so he's entitled to—let's not do 30 tons—three
tons, he's entitled to two tons of rubble and the other guy's
entitled to one ton, and he recognizes this stone, so now he
gets two tons of rubble minus one stone. You know what I
mean? This counts towards his total tonnage that he takes away. Okay?
Because but this is his, so it's not as if in addition
to his two tons, it's part of his two tons. It counts
on his side of the ledger. Okay? Well, yes, but the גמרא
Gemara is going to discuss what's less obvious is does the other
guy get another whole stone parallel to that or like let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara מדקתני רואין, Midiktani ro'in, since it
says that you determine which were the you know whether the broken
stones came more from the top or the bottom and so on,
מכלל דאיכא למיקם עלייהו, Miklal de'ika lmeikem alaiau, it seems like that
it's able to determine how the building collapsed and whether you know
the from the top or from the bottom and whose stones are
whose. אי בחבצה נפל, Iy b'chafsa nafal, חבצה chafsa רש"י Rashi says
means that it basically was like some type of a—I don't know
how they translate the word chafsa—רש"י Rashi says it means that the
foundation, the foundation was sort of shattered. How do they translate it?
Pressure? Pressure? Okay. Oh, so I guess pressure from the top, so
it like collapsed down.
It relates to חבצה. chavatz. Okay.
So anyway, so something about the foundation either fell down you know
collapsed in its place from the top or the foundation was shattered.
Okay and then it would be the question of the top or
the bottom of the rubble. אי בחבטה נפל Iy b'chavta nafal or
if it's some type of impact which רש"י Rashi says actually means
like the top of the building fell down and therefore the top
section is further away and the bottom section is closer. So presumably
you can determine it. Okay. So if that's true and then you
do it based on that assessment, אי הכי רישא מאי חולקין? Iy
hachi reisha mai cholkin? So why does the beginning say that you
just divide equally? נחזי, Nachzei, why don't we assess it? אי בחבטה
נפל, Iy b'chavta nafal, if it was through a type of a
you know of a collapse of the top falling down, עילייתא אתבור,
elayata itbar, then the top stuff was the one that broke. You
know, the top fell down, they're the one more distance, they hit
with the greatest impact, and most likely the top story are the
broken stones. אי בחבצה נפל, Iy b'chafsa nafal, if it was type
pressure or some type of a shattering of the foundation,
תתייתא אתבור, tata'ata itbar, then it's the bottom level that has the
broken stones. So the obvious point is, you know, in some circumstances
you can tell, some you can't, and when you can't tell you
do it proportionally and when you can tell you do it based
on your ability to tell. But the גמרא Gemara wants to understand
what are the circumstances when you won't be able to tell? If
you're assuming that you often can, what are the circumstances you won't
be able to tell? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: lo, צריכא, tzricha, you need it for the following case. דנפל
בלילה, D'nafal balaila, it fell at night, nobody saw it, there's no
eyewitnesses, so we don't know how it fell. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ונחזייה בצפרא, v'nachzeihu b'tzafra, okay, but you wake up in the
morning and let's take a look. Do you have one collapsed pile
of rubble or did something you know fall at a you know
is it spread out over a distance? You can tell which way
it fell. No, דפנינהו, d'paniyeihu, it got cleared away. We have a
very efficient public services and they cleared it away before anybody could
see how it fell. So the גמרא Gemara says, ונחזיה מאן פנינהו
ולשאליה, v'nachzeih man paniyeihu u'lishaileih, so let's ask the people who cleared
it away what would it—what did it look like? דפנינהו בני רשות
הרבים, D'panini bnei reshus harabim, no, the people of רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, they all chipped in, everybody, they did a big קול קורא,
kol koreh, everybody turned out in the middle of the night and
everybody participated before anybody—and nobody was paying attention.
Now, of course, just for you, you who own the building, just
for you.
No, you were away somewhere.
It could be like a small like storage area
in רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
It could be. I mean a בית ועליה bayis v'aliyah normally assume
a living domicile, but ואזלו לעלמא va'azlu l'alma
and we don't know any of them. They were just some strangers
passing by and they all did this great public deed.
All right, anyway, and who uploaded it on YouTube?
All right, whatever. Anyway, the point is the question—the question doesn't bother
me so much. The משנה mishnah is saying when you can tell,
you can tell, and when you can't tell, you do it equally.
I mean, you know, whatever the case is is the case is.
Anyway, the גמרא—now Gemara the גמרא Gemara gets to a more interesting
halakhic question. The גמרא Gemara says,
ונחזי ברשות דמאן יתבי, v'lichzi bireshus deman yasvi, דהוי אידך המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה. d'havei idach hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. Why don't we say
where are the stones right now? So all of the stones are
in my yard, okay, then I don't know, I own the ground
level. Okay, let's say it's all my yard. You don't have yard
rights, you only have the house rights. Or let's say I have
the front yard, you have the back yard for argument's sake. So
all the stones in the front yard,
I'm the מוחזק muchzak and if you want to claim they're yours,
you're המוציא מחבירו hamotzi mechavero and the same for the stones in
the back yard in the reverse. So let's just see whose רשות
reshus they're sitting in. Now, I won't be able to claim that
if let's say all the stones are in my yard, I can't
say they're all mine, because clearly you own a third of them.
Okay, but I could claim which two thirds are mine because I'm
the מוחזק. muchzak. All right, so why don't we just see and
why don't we just see whose
רשות reshus there is? וליהוי אידך המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. v'lehevei idach
hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. לא, צריכא, tzricha, you need it דיתבין בחצר
דתרוייהו, d'yasvin bechatzer detarvaihu, they both equally own the yard, so nobody
is מוחזק. muchzak. אי נמי ברשות הרבים, Ee nami birshus harabim, or
it fell right into the public domain. ואי בעית אימא, V'ee ba'is
eima, if I want I could tell you שותפין בכי האי גוונא
לא קפדי אהדדי. shutfim bechai hai gavna lo kapdi ahadadi. Let's say
it's my yard, I own the house, but you know, I sold
Michael the top story, but it's my bottom story and my yard.
Nevertheless, I'm not considered מוחזק. muchzak. Since Michael is living in my
top story, and every time he comes home he walks through the
yard, in general I of course let him bring out his lawn
chair and sit in my yard, I let his kids play in
the yard. So technically it's my yard, but implicitly he has rights
to it. I have allowed him to use it. This is very
interesting. He doesn't have legal rights, but implicitly, the גמרא Gemara, says
לא קפדי, lo kapdi, I'm totally okay with you going ahead and
making regular use of the yard. Therefore, when the stones are in
the yard, I'm not more מוחזק muchzak than you. That's a big
חידוש. chiddush. You would think at the end of the day, I'm
the one with legal rights, I'm considered מוחזק, muchzak, but since practically,
you know, מוחזק muchzak also is a practical thing, is it physically
under my control or not? So even though it's technically in my
property that I own, since practically it's a space that Michael has
equal practical rights, not legal rights but practical presence, he's considered an
equal מוחזק. muchzak. So I find that quite fascinating. All right, now
the גמרא Gemara's says like this, אם היה אחד מהם מכיר, im
hayah echad meihem makir, now if one of them recognized their stuff,
they take their stuff and then you count it towards their side
of the ledger. So the גמרא Gemara says והלה מה טוען? vehala
mah to'ein?
So I say, oh, this gorgeous... we were just in Israel and
we went... I went on the tunnel tours twice because I went
a week before my family, so I took my son who's learning
in Israel to the tunnel tours and then my family came and
said we're going on the tunnel tours. Anyway, whenever... if you ever
go on the tunnel tours, you know they walk you along, you
know, the Western Walls there, you know, all the way down. Anyway,
they always stop and show you, you know, that big stone, right?
It's like it goes out what is it like... it's like 20
yards or something or I don't know, it's super long, it's like
50 tons, okay, it's like the... I think it's like the heaviest
building stone, like the third heaviest building stone they found in the
world and nobody can figure out how they raised it up to
get it on top of it. Anyway, fine. Okay, so I've got
these gorgeous stones. Oh, that one I recognize, that's mine. All that
other stuff, yeah, that's yours. But I claim, I go ahead and
I recognize the really nice stones and those are mine and I'm
keeping them for myself. So what are you saying? Are you saying
no, they're mine? Are you admitting to me?
You don't know. So right, you're saying okay, pick it up and
go.
Exactly. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, והלה מה טוען? vehala mah to'ein?
So what's the other guy saying?
So אי דקאמר אין, ee deka'amar in, yeah, you're right, it is
yours, פשיטא, pishita, then I don't need the משנה Mishnah to tell
me that I get it. אי, Ee, all right, I understand. ואי
לא אמר אין, v'ee lo amar in, if you don't say it,
למה נוטל? lamah notel? We just got through saying we're equally מוחזק,
muchzak, so why... I say it's mine and you say it's not
yours... I say it's mine. אלא דאמר
ליה איני יודע. Ella de'amar lei eini yodeia. The obvious answer is
you say you don't know and I say I do
know.
לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב נחמן. Leima tehevei tiyuvta deRav Nachman. דאתמר מנה
לי בידך והלה אומר איני יודע. De'itmar maneh li beyadecha vehala omer
eini yodeia. רב
הונא ורב יהודה אמרי חייב. Rav Huna v'Rav Yehuda amri chayav. ברי
ושמא ברי עדיף. Bari v'shema bari adif. רב נחמן ורבי יוחנן אמרי
פטור. Rav Nachman v'Rabbi Yochanan amri patur. So
if according to Rav Nachman that מוחזק muchzak is better, just because
I say I recognize the stone, why should I win it? You
know, now the question is, well one minute, the reason that my
ברי bari doesn't win is because I'm trying to take money out
of your pocket because you're מוחזק. muchzak. But here we just got
through saying that nobody is מוחזק. muchzak. So why doesn't my ברי
bari win? It's a ברי bari without a מוחזק muchzak against it.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafot asks that question. So take a look at
תוספות. Tosafot, לימא תהוי
תיובתא. Leima tehevei tiyuvta. to לרב נחמן. le-Rav Nachman. אומר תוספות, Omer
Tosfos, דאמר פטור. d'amar patur. ואף על גב דטעמא דרב נחמן משום
דאוקי ממונא בחזקת מריה, ve-af al gav de-ta'ama de-Rav Nachman mishum de-ukimei
mamona be-chezkat marei, the reason ברי bari doesn't win is 'cause I
can't take money out of your pocket because you have a חזקה.
chazaka. והכא אוקי דקיימי ברשות הרבים, ve-hacha uki de-kaimi be-reshut ha-rabbim, we
said it's in the public domain, או בחצר שאינה של שניהם, o
be-chatzer she-eina shel sheneihem, or it should be חצר של שניהם. chatzer
shel sheneihem. שאין אחד מוחזק יותר מחבירו. she-ein echad muchzak yoter me-chaveiro.
Nobody has more חזקה, chazaka, so why doesn't my ברי bari win
out? What do you mean it's a קשיא kasha on לרב נחמן?
le-Rav Nachman? It's a ברי bari without a counter חזקה? chazaka? מכל
מקום בהכי חשיב מוחזק שאנו יודעים שחצי שלו. Mi-kol makom be-hachi chashiv
muchzak she-anu yodim she-chatzi shelo. לכך פרך שפיר. le-kach parach shapir. This
is very interesting. It sort of gets back to, and this is
very evocative of the first פרק, you know, where we're both holding
onto it and we say the fact that we're both holding onto
it creates some type of equal מוחזקות muchzakos or an objective ספק
safek like a presumption that we're both in control. So the fact
that the building collapsed and we know that half of the material
is mine and half is yours means that even if it's not
in either of our physical possession, if I'm claiming a particular stone
is mine, I'm trying to take half of it out of your
חזקה. chazaka. You got the idea? We know of all this rubble,
you own 50% and I own 50%. If I'm claiming a particular
stone is mine, in any particular stone there's a presumption that you're
a 50% owner and I'm a 50% because that's true about the
whole rubble. So a claim that it's all mine is trying to
take half of it out of your חזקה. chazaka. Okay, out of
the presumption that you have half right to everything. Okay?
ואמר עוד בפרק השואל כל ממון המוטל בספק חשיב כאילו הם מוחזקים
בה, ve-amar od be-perek ha-sho'el kol mamon ha-muttal be-safek chashiv ke-ilu hem
muchzakim bah, which is really essentially the same point. So that's a
very interesting conceptual point. We've right now introduced two new ways of
thinking of חזקה. chazaka. One is, it's not physically in my חצר,
chatzer, but it's in a חצר chatzer that I have rights to,
or that I don't even have legal rights to, practically I'm present
and I'm allowed to use it. That means that I'm considered an
equal מוחזק muchzak even though it's legally your חצר. chatzer. That's one
idea. The other idea is, it's not in either of our חצרות,
chatzeros, but each one of us is considered a מוחזק muchzak by
virtue of the fact that we know that we have equal ownership
of this pile. So when I come to claim that a particular
stone is mine, I'm a ברי bari and you're a שמא, shema,
it's still like I'm trying to take it away from your חזקה
chazaka because of our knowledge that we're equal owners of this pile,
that we're each half owners.
That's the same way לרב נחמן le-Rav Nachman in the same case
with the מנה maneh said it.
The same way my ברי bari can't make me take a hundred
dollars out of your pocket when you say איני יודע, eini yodea,
my ברי, bari, says the גמרא, Gemara shouldn't let me take the
whole stone away from you. Exactly. Exactly. So let's see what the
גמרא's Gemara answer is. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, כדאמר רב
נחמן כגון שיש עסק שבועה ביניהם. ke-d'amar Rav Nachman k'gon she-yesh esek
shevua beineihem.
The same way רב נחמן Rav Nachman says in another way to
explain why you're why you're able to win, that there's a שבועה
shevua and because there's a שבועה shevua between them and a שבועה
shevua can't be made it lets the other side win, we'll spell
this out, הכא נמי כגון שיש עסק שבועה ביניהם. hacha nami k'gon
she-yesh esek shevua beineihem. The same is true here. היכי דמי עסק
שבועה? heichi dami esek shevua? What would be the case, an example
of this? כדרבה דאמר רבה מנה לי בידך. ke-de-Rabba d'amar Rabba maneh
li be-yadecha. I say, Michael, you owe me a hundred dollars. ואמר
אין לך בידי אלא חמישים. ve-amar ein lecha be-yadi ela chamishim. Yes,
I admit I owe you 50. והשאר, ve-hashar, so you're מודה במקצת,
modeh be-miktzat, you're חייב שבועה chayav shevua on the rest. But what
about the rest? והשאר איני יודע. ve-hashar eini yodea. I don't know
about the rest. So you have to make a שבועה shevua about
the rest because you admitted to half, מודה במקצת, modeh be-miktzat, but
you don't know. So you can't make a שבועה. shevua. מתוך שאינו
יכול להישבע משלם, mitoch she-eino yachol lishava meshalem,
because he can't make a שבועה shevua he has to pay. So
therefore, that's a case where I'm a ברי bari and Michael's a
שמא shema and I win. I don't win by virtue that my
ברי bari lets me take money out of his pocket. I win
by virtue that the ברי bari created a שבועה shevua and his
שמא shema now he can't make the שבועה shevua and therefore I
win for his inability to make the שבועה. shevua. So here too,
we're arguing over the stones and I say, Michael,
those five stones you're holding onto right now, you know, three of
them actually I recognize that they're all mine. And Michael says, look,
I admit that three of them are yours. Here, take them back
or whatever. I'll go get them. Okay. But the other two actually
are mine. Okay. So then he would have to make a שבועה...
shevua... the other two might be mine. Might be mine. I'm not
sure. So because he can't make a שבועה shevua on the other
two, I win even on the other two. Okay. It's totally not
פשט pshat of the משנה. mishna. פשט pshat of the משנה mishna
is not that I win because I got you to make a...
I forced a שבועה shevua on you. פשט pshat of the משנה
mishna is I win because I made a definite claim. All right.
And that either is because a definite claim wins out against חזקה,
chazaka, or maybe makes us challenge the idea of
חזקה. chazaka. But here the גמרא Gemara is assuming that each party
is considered מוחזק muchzak and that's why it asks this question on
רב נחמן. Rav Nachman.
Yes, are you positive those two stones are not yours and they're
his? He'll take the vow and then you won't be able to
collect.
Right, exactly. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ועולה
לו מן החשבון. ve-oleh lo min ha-cheshbon. When I go ahead and
I take those stones that I now have claimed are mine, that
goes towards my side of the ledger. Okay? So fine. So now
I can only take, you know, two tons minus two stones. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says, that's obvious. But what's not
obvious is what happens on your side of the ledger. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
סבר רב. savar Rav. meaning so what רבא Rava says is, I
get so, you know, I get these two stones, we're dividing up
the property, okay? I just now took two stones that I had
identified as mine, they weighed 100 pounds. You now are gonna we're
now gonna give you 100 pounds of stones. Which 100? So רבא
Rava says, you'll get 100 pounds of the broken stones. I took
two nice big stones because I recognized they're mine. You get 100
pounds of the broken. Now תוספות says it doesn't I think תוספות
somebody says here, it doesn't literally mean just the broken. Why should
you get only the broken? But you get two you get what'd
I say two pounds or 200 pounds two pounds whatever I said.
Anyway, these two stones were worth 200 pounds, you're now going to
get 200 pounds of the mixture. It's a mixture of broken and
and whole ones. So I was able to take out the whole
ones as knowing they were definitely mine, you'll get your 200 pounds
of the proportional mixture of whatever is there. That's what רבא says.
All right. So where were we? למימר לפי חשבון שבורות. le-meimar lefi
cheshbon shevuros. אמר כיון דאמר איני יודע ריעא, Amar keivan de-amar eini
yodeia reia, since you said you don't know, you're in a disadvantaged
position. I know, therefore I take this and for everything else we
just it's an equal distribution of broken and whole ones. That makes
sense as I would say פשטא דמשנה. peshata de-mishna. אמר ליה אביי,
Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said back, אדרבה, Adaraba, I'll say the
opposite. האי ריעא, Hai reia, the guy who took the two whole
stones, he's in a worse position. Why? מדאני ידעי וטפי לא ידעי,
mi-de-hani yadai ve-tfei lo yadai, I recognized these two whole stones as
mine. But the other ten whole stones I didn't recognize as mine.
So why don't we claim, so you get these two and the
other guy gets the other ten because you know since you apparently
you know which ones are yours. מדאני ידעי וטפי לא ידעי, mi-de-hani
yadai ve-tfei lo yadai, since you know that these are yours and
you don't know the others, תו לית ליה. tu leis lei. You're
implicitly saying that the other whole stones aren't yours and they're his.
Okay, which is a very interesting read. ואידך כולהו דהאיך נינהו, ve-idakh
kulehu de-haikh ninhu, and the other whole stones all go to the
other guy. אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said לפי
חשבון שלמות. lefi cheshbon shelmos. No no no. So we're not going
to go that far to say that you you hurt your position
by saying that. But we're going to say is, if I get
to take these two stones I recognize as mine and I take
them and they weigh 200 pounds, you now get to take 200
pounds of other whole stones. I got whole stones and that I
recognized as mine, you get not a mixture, you get whole stones
whether you do or don't recognize if I get whole you get
whole ones. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay so we're still going
to keep an equal distribution of equal of the whole stones are
equally divided and the broken ones are equally divided. I just get
to keep the ones I know I just get from amongst the
whole stones that were equally divided, I get to keep the ones
that I know are mine. So then the גמרא Gemara. says so
what good does it do you? Everybody's getting an equal amount of
whole stones. One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי מאי
כמהני ליה? ei hachi mai ka-mahani lei? If everybody's getting an equal
amount of whole stones, what difference does it make if they're the
ones you recognize or not the ones you recognize? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, למבנא רווחא, le-mivna ravcha, maybe it's a wide stone.
אי נמי טינא דמעבדא, ei nami tina de-ma'avda, or maybe it's good
plaster. Meaning yes, we can all get the same tonnage of whole
stones and the same number of whole stones, but quality, some are
better than others. Okay? So that's why so that's why it matters.
But at the end of the day, recognizing that they're yours and
by the way, that's also in the answer to רב דחמן Rav
Dachman about the ברי ושמא bari ve-shema because I don't really walk
away with more money, more value, you know, like in a ברי
ושמא bari ve-shema case I claim you owe me 100 dollars can
I take 100 dollars out of your pocket? At the end of
the day, we're still getting an equal distribution of whole stones and
an equal distribution of broken stones. The only value that my claim
has is to let me from within the stones identify which ones
are mine or not. It's not the same like degree of ish
of consequence.
You can think of it that way otherwise you even though logically
you could have the more rational position you would disincentivize people to
tell the truth.
Well, certainly אביי's extreme version of it, yeah, absolutely. Right of course,
it's it's clever.
Right. Right. Okay, let's look at the next משנה. mishna.
הבית והעליה, ha-bayit ve-ha-aliyah, you have a house and a top story.
ורש"י ve-Rashi points out, it's clear from the way the גמרא Gemara
understands it, as opposed to the first משנה mishna where it was
a split ownership, here it's a rental situation. I own the whole
house, you have this a lot, right? People have two family homes
and they rent out the top story. נפחתה העליה. niphseta ha-aliyah. Now
the top one broke and what's going to be broken is that
the floor of it presumably broke. Okay or
some some so you know this happens all the time in rental
situations, right? My roof is leaking, I can't live in my house,
you have to come and fix it. If you don't fix it,
you have to get rent me out another house, etc. What's the
story? ואין בעל הבית רוצה לתקן. ve-ein Ba'al ha-bayit rotzeh letaken. The
בעל
הבית
Ba'al
ha-bayit who owns the bottom story,
doesn't want to come fix it. הרי בעל העליה יורד ודר למטה
עד שיתקן לו את העליה. harei Ba'al ha-aliyah yored ve-dar lemata ad
she-yitaken lo et ha-aliyah. Okay? So fine. You don't want to get
fix it? You still have to provide me a place to live.
I'm going to come live with you till you fix it. That's
a good
incentive. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi Omer, Rabbi Yossi says,
התחתון נותן את התקרה והעליון את המעזיבה. hatachton noten et hatikra vehaelyon
et hamaziva. Now, he actually says that if what happened is that
the floor broke, you understand that my floor is your ceiling, okay,
if I'm living in the עליה. So he says actually, you know,
these are all these questions in the co-ops, right? I mean, it's
very clear like, you know, up to the wall is the buyer's
responsibility, inside the wall is the co-op's responsibility, right, exactly where, you
know, where those lines end. So here he said, you know, you
the owner, you have to go, you have to put the beams,
you have to put the whole structural stuff. But I will at
least have to put the plaster of the floor. That's my responsibility.
That's like it really is like the front of the walls and
behind the walls. I have to put the plaster, you have to
put the beams. Okay, let's look at the גמרא. Gemara נפחתה בכמה.
Nifchata bekama. Oh, I knew it was the ceiling, right?
טיפיחת והמעזיבה? Tipichat vehamaziva?
Yeah, but the מעזיבה maziva is the plaster, okay? It's your ceiling.
No, it's your ceiling, it's my floor. Oh, okay.
And wasn't the case of פחת המעזיבה? pachat hamaziva?
Yes, it's your מעזיבה maziva from the perspective of the guy in
the bottom, it's his ceiling. It's the plaster of his ceiling. From
the perspective of the guy on the top, it's the plaster of
his floor.
Okay. So, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
It's also why it's called תקרה tikra and not and it's not
called floor. It's on the perspective of the guy in the bottom.
What?
It's a renter. The guy on the top is the renter... is
the rent-ee, is the whatever, I mean the rent-or. Yeah, the guy
on the bottom is, what do you call him? Landlord.
Okay, anyway, נפחתה בכמה. Nifchata bekama. How much is considered that the
place is uninhabitable and that gives me a right to go... I
mean, even with a lesser thing you might have an obligation to
fix it, but what stage do I have a right to go
ahead and live in your place? So, and this is like a
hole in the floor. So רבא אמר ברובא, Rava amar beruba, the
majority of it.
אביי ושמואל אמר בארבעה. Abaye v'Shmuel amar bearbaa. It's enough that it's
just like, you know, four אמות. amos. So actually ארבעה arbaa is
טפחים. tefachim. Yeah, ארבעה arbaa is not ארבע, arba, ארבעה arbaa is
four טפחים, tefachim, which is very small, which is like a foot
by a foot. Okay. Now you would think logically it might be
somewhere between those two extremes, okay? But anyway, so let's take a
look. רבא אמר ברובא אבל בארבעה לא, Rava amar beruba aval bearbaa
lo, but with four it's not enough. אדם דר חציו למטה וחציו
למעלה. Adam dar chetzyo lemata vechetzyo lemala. So I say we've got
a foot space here that's rickety and broken... so okay, I say
to you, what can't you do in that foot? Well, I would
have put my dresser there. I'll tell you what. I'll say, I'll
put your, we'll keep your dresser downstairs in my apartment. Okay. So
רבא says, you know what, that's tolerable. I can live upstairs, and
when I need to go get my clothes, I'll walk down and
get, you know, get them from the dresser in your room, which
does not seem so reasonable.
ושמואל אמר בארבעה. U'shmuel amar bearbaa. No, four טפחים tefachim is enough
to make it uninhabitable. אין אדם דר חציו למטה וחציו למעלה. Ein
adam dar chetzyo lemata vechetzyo lemala. ארבעה Arbaa is already a space
that you do a necessary use. And if I don't have it
here and have to use half of it downstairs, that is not
a reasonable arrangement. And therefore that gives me the right not only
to demand that you fix it, but to move downstairs with you
if you haven't fixed it. Okay. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? Now what's
the case? What is the case that I the renter have an
obligation to provide you an alternate place to live if I'm not
fixing the problem? אי דאמר ליה עליה זו. Ee d'amar lei aliya
zu. If I say I'm renting you this, you know, second story,
אזדא. Azda. Then you, okay, it's yours. You have to deal with
whatever problems there are. Okay, which is an interesting question, like why
we assume that, right? If I rent out a house and it
starts to get a leaky roof, right? I presumably that's the responsibility
of the landlord, right? I mean, but the גמרא assumes and the
way רש״י Rashi adds to it, it's a phrase called like מזלך
גרם. mazlacha gram. It's your bad luck. You know, maybe you should
have checked it out beforehand to see how good the roof was.
I mean, let's say, let's say it's a case where it's nobody's
fault, okay? It was a nice, good, sturdy roof, torrential rain, a
tree collapsed, it made a hole in the roof and so on.
What are the like secular laws? It's still the landlord's responsibility?
Yes, but you probably don't and you probably can move and get
out of your lease too.
Okay, but either the landlord, but
if the landlord has to pay, yeah...
so the, so the גמרא here assumes otherwise if it's nobody's fault,
then it's your bad luck, okay? Which is a surprising idea, as
if you just said this particular thing I'm lending you, it's still
rented to you. Go ahead, use it with a leaky roof. אלא
דאמר ליה עליה סתם. Ela d'amar lei aliya stam. So I didn't
say this one. I said, I'm renting you a second story. So
it has to mean an inhabitable one. So it's not this in
particular. So like think about a hotel, right? A hotel you rent
a room, it's not like a particular room. If they can't put
you up in this one, they have to put you up in
another one. לוגר ליה אחריתי. Logar lei achriti. So why does he
move downstairs? Then he should just rent him out a another place,
right? But why does he move... what's the case where he's still
obligated to provide him a place but the guy... rather than renting
another place, the guy goes downstairs. So the גמרא says, אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, לא צריכא דאמר ליה עליה זו שאני משכיר לך. lo
tsericha de-amar lei aliyah zu she-ani maskir lecha.
So רבא said you made an explicit condition. This story, this second
story that I'm renting out to you, כי סלקא סליק בהדה, ki
salka salik bahada, if it's in good condition you can use it,
go up with it, וכי נחית נחית בהדה, ve-chi nachis nachis bahada,
if it collapses,
come down with it, you can live with me. So the גמרא
says at that we don't need a משנה Mishnah to tell you
if you made an explicit condition. אי הכי מאי לממרא, ei hachi
mai l'memra, it's obvious. אלא אמר רב אשי, Ela amar Rav Ashi,
דאמר ליה עליה זו שעל גבי בית זה אני משכיר לך. de-amar
lei aliyah zu she-al gabi bayis zeh ani maskir lecha. I am
renting you this story that is on top of this house. By
saying the words 'on top of this house' what you mean is,
you're it's interpreted whether you mean it or not, it's interpreted as
an implicit condition that this house is sort of the is responsible,
you know, is part of what you have rights to, if something
goes wrong with the upper story.
דאשעביד בית לעליה. de-ashabeid bayis l'aliyah. Since he said the עליה on
top of this house, the בית bayis sort of is subjugated, you
know, is like is leaned towards the upper one. You have rights
to the בית to ensure that you will be able to live
where you can live. So I don't have to rent you another
place, but you do have a right to move downstairs. And thus
one more sentence, וכי הא דאמר רבין בר רב אדא אמר רבי
יצחק, ve-chi ha de-amar Ravin bar Rav Adda amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מעשה
באחד שאמר לחברו דלית שעל גבי פרסק זה אני מוכר לך. maaseh
be-echad she-amar l'chavero delis she-al gabi parsak zeh ani mocher lecha. I
am selling you this vine that's on top of this tree or
that's wound around this tree, נעקר הפרסק, ne-ekar ha-parsak, and the tree
was
uprooted, ובא מעשה לפני רבי חייא, u-va maaseh lifnei Rabbi Chiyya, the
case came to רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiyya, ואמר חייב אתה להעמיד לו
פרסק כל זמן שהדלית קיימת. ve-amar chayav ata l'haamid lo parsak kol
zman she-ha-delis kayames. You have to replant the tree as long as
the vine is still there because you sold him a vine that
was growing around a tree, not a vine that was on a
dead tree. So it's not exactly the same, but the point being
that if you mentioned this other object, it creates it's part then
of the responsibility. So the same way there it was a responsibility
that the vine would be attached to a growing tree, here too
the house has to ensure that you have a place to live.
Okay, but what to me is more fascinating is that if you
just סתם stam have a rental agreement and I rent you a
house and the house collapses that I don't have to go ahead
and provide you with another house. But תוספות points out, I know
we're like one minute over but just we really have to read
this one word in תוספות because it's just so critical to understanding
this. ואי ve-ei
look at the תוספות, אי דאמר ליה עליה זו ונפלה אזדה ליה,
ei de-amar lei aliyah zu ve-nafla azda leh, if the house collapsed
it's your problem because I rented you just this one house. ויתן
לו שכרו שכבר דר, ve-yiten lo secharo she-kevar dar, שאם דר חצי
יתן חצי. she-im dar chatzi yiten chatzi. I don't have to pay
you the rent for the rest of the month, okay, I rented
it for a month and it collapsed half the month. Obviously I
don't have to pay you the rent for the other half of
the month, but on the other hand, you don't have to go
ahead and find me another place to live. Okay, so it is
fair in the sense that I'm not going to pay for time
I'm not that I don't pay for for an uninhabitable place. But
what it's also saying is, but you as the landlord don't have
to go ahead and work to find me an alternative place. Basically
I just get out of my lease and I pay for what
I've already rented. All right, we will end today. Basically.